Robert Preston Taylor papers, Inclusive: 1945-2002, undated, Bulk: 1950-1966
Baylor University, The Texas Collection
Robert Preston Taylor papers
Inclusive: 1945-2002, undated, Bulk: 1950-1966
Baylor University, The Texas Collection http://www.baylor.edu/lib/texas/
3597
Taylor, Robert P. (Robert Preston), 1909-1997
9 document boxes 1 OVZ box
The Robert Preston Taylor papers primarily document the military career of the chaplain after his service in World War II. The collection includes military records, sermons, photographs, books, correspondence, and audio recordings. Items from his career at Southwestern Baptist Theological Seminary and post retirement are also included.
Administrative Information
Physical Description
General condition: Good.
Biography/Profile
Robert Preston Taylor was born in Henderson, Texas, on April 11, 1909. He attended the Jacksonville College Academy (High School) and Jacksonville College (Junior College) prior to enrolling at Baylor University where he was active with the Ministers Association. He graduated in 1933 and went on to receive Master of Theology and Doctor of Theology degrees from the Southwestern Baptist Theological Seminary in Fort Worth, Texas.
While serving as pastor at South Fort Worth Baptist Church in 1938, Taylor received word that the Chaplains Division of the War Department was seeking men to volunteer in the chaplaincy of the armed services. He volunteered as a reserve, serving shortly that summer at Fort Hood. In 1940, he volunteered for a full year of service and was assigned to the Army Air Corp and the 31st Infantry Regiment, Philippine Division located at Barksdale Field, Louisiana. The division was activated and arrived in the Philippines in May 1941.
While serving his tour, Chaplain Taylor was taken as a prisoner of war in the Philippines. He was held captive for forty-two months, enduring the harshest of conditions in camps as well as the Bataan Death March and Hell Ships. In 1945, Taylor was liberated while encamped in Manchuria. He arrived in San Francisco, California, on November 1, 1945, and was given 105 days of convalescent leave, during which he decided to continue serving as a military chaplain. His career took him to camps across the United States, and in 1962, he was appointed Chief Chaplain of the United Stated Air Force at the rank of Major General. He held this position until his military retirement in 1966. In 1966, Chaplain Taylor began work in the development office at Southwestern Baptist Theological Seminary in Fort Worth, Texas. He retired as a civilian in 1973.
Robert Preston Taylor married Mildred Good in 1950, and they had one son, Robert Preston Taylor, Jr. The elder Taylor was honored for his services during World War II with a Silver Star, Bronze Star, and the Presidential Unit Citation with two oak leaf clusters. In addition, the Joint Forces Staff College Chapel in Norfolk, Virginia was dedicated in his name in 2002. He is also one of three men enshrined in the Baylor University Ring of Honor on campus. The Chaplain, Major General Robert Preston Taylor Memorial Endowed Scholarship was established in 2004 at the George W. Truett Theological Seminary to support students preparing for careers as chaplains in the United Sates Armed Forces, National Guard, or Reserves.
Chaplain, Major General Robert Preston Taylor died February 1, 1997, and is buried in the Field of Honor at Restland Memorial Park in Dallas, Texas.
Scope and Content
The Robert Preston Taylor papers are inclusive of Taylor’s military career after his release as a prisoner of war during World War II. The Correspondence series includes primarily thank you letters, congratulations, and invitations for speaking engagements. The General series includes speech notes, event programs, and reports from throughout Taylor’s military and civilian careers.
Military Records include official orders, newsletters written by the chaplain, appointment books, correspondence, sermons, and activity reports. The Photographs series documents military portraits, luncheons, dinners, event attendance, and celebrations. Minimal personal photos are included.
Publications includes a history of the United States Air Force Chaplain Services, several books recounting experiences of soldiers involved in the Bataan Death March, clippings, recruiting materials, and a history of the 31st Infantry Division. Audiovisual materials include sermons and addresses given while Chaplain Taylor was active in the Air Force as well as after his retirement.
Arrangement
The collection had no previous discernable arrangement. Many of the photographs and correspondence were collected in binders and plastic sleeves; they have been removed to accommodate preservation of the materials. Captions formerly taped to fronts of the photographs have also been removed, the information was transferred to the backs of items. The collection is currently in six series: I. Correspondence, II. General, III. Military Records, IV. Photographs, V. Publications, and VI. Audiovisual.
Access Restrictions
All requests for copying of materials must be submitted to The Texas Collection in writing. Please use the Request Form for Copying Materials sheet. Unpublished materials authored or otherwise produced by the creator (s) of this collection are in the public domain. There are no restrictions on use. Copyright status for other collection materials is unknown. Transmission or reproduction of materials protected by U.S. Copyright Law (Title 17, U.S.C.) beyond that allowed by fair use requires the written permission of the copyright owners. Works not in the public domain cannot be commercially exploited without permission of the copyright owners. Responsibility for any use rests exclusively with the user.
Acquisition Information
Accession No. 3597. Acquired 2004-01-26
Related Resources
Related references
“Chaplain (Major General) Robert P. Taylor.” U.S. Air Force. Accessed 2021 March 3.
Find A Grave, Inc. “MG Robert Preston Taylor.” Memorial #87318581. Databases. Accessed 2021 January 25.
Keith, Billy. Days of Anguish, Days of Hope. Garden City, New York: Doubleday & Company, Inc., 1972.
“Red Cross Meeting.” The Waco Citizen (Waco, Texas), 1971 July 1.
Index Terms
Subjects (Persons)
Taylor, Robert P. (Robert Preston), 1909-1997
Subjects (Organizations)
United States. Air Force -- Chaplains.
Subjects
Baptists -- Sermons.; Ex-prisoners of war -- United States.; Military chaplains -- Baptists.; Military orders.; World War, 1939-1945 -- Chaplains.; World War, 1939-1945 -- Veterans -- United States.
Genres
Appointment Books.; Audiocassettes.; Clippings (Books, newspapers, etc.); Correspondence.; Newsletters.; Open reel audiotapes.; Photographs.; Programs (Publications).; Sermons.; Yearbooks.
- Correspondence, 1945-1992, undated; 1
  Administrative Information
  Physical Description
  General condition: Good.
  Biography/Profile
  The correspondence series is dated 1945-1992. A primary portion of the included documents are congratulatory letters on military promotions and retirement. Thank you letters, invitations for speaking engagements, and personal correspondence are also included. The series is arranged in chronological order and in good condition.
  - From Southwestern Baptist Theological Seminary, 1945-1966 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Nomination, Deputy Chief of Air Force Chaplains (Brigadier General), 1958 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Congratulations, Promotion to Deputy Chief of Air Force Chaplains, 1958 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Congratulations, Promotion to Deputy Chief of Air Force Chaplains (1 of 2), 1958 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Congratulations, Promotion to Deputy Chief of Air Force Chaplains (2 of 2), 1958 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Appointment Letters and Cards, 1958-1966 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - General, 1958-1977, undated (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Congratulations, Appointment as Chief Air Force Chaplain (1 of 2), 1962 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Congratulations, Appointment as Chief Air Force Chaplain (2 of 2), 1962 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Thank You Letters from United States Air Force Academy Cadets, 1964 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Appointment to Southwestern Baptist Theological Seminary, 1966 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Congratulations on Military Retirement, 1966 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Engagements, Meetings and Speaking, 1966 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Retirement from United States Air Force, 1966 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Congratulations on Appointment at Southwestern Baptist Theological Seminary, 1966-1969 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Retirement from Southwestern Baptist Theological Seminary, 1973 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Speaking Engagements, 1973-1975 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - General, 1977-1992 (Box 2, Folder 9)
- General, 1951-2002, undated; 2
  The General series is dated 1951-2002 and is primarily speech notes and event programs. Programs document Chaplain Taylor’s invited sermons, including his final military worship service at Carswell Air Force Base which was located outside of Fort Worth, Texas. Other programs include receptions for the Chapel of Four Chaplains Awards Banquet and the dedication of the Robert P. Taylor Memorial Chapel at the Joint Forces Staff College in Norfolk, Virginia. The series is arranged in chronological order and in good condition.
  - Speech Notes, undated (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Bulletin, Kirkwood Baptist Church, Atlanta, Georgia, Speaking Engagement, 1951 (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Speech Notes, 1958-1966 (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Baccalaureate Programs, Speaking Engagements, 1963 (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - Texas Navy Honorary Admirable Certificate, 1964 (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - Program, Protestant Worship Service, Carswell Air Force Base, TX, Final Military Worship Service, 1966 (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - Reports, Home Mission Board, Southern Baptist Convention, 1967 (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - The Chapel of Four Chaplains Awards Banquet (Recipient), 1976 (Box 2, Folder 17)
  - Program, Robert P. Taylor Memorial Chapel Dedication, 2002 (Box 2, Folder 18)
- Military Records, 1946-1966; 3
  Military records are dated 1946-1966 and are inclusive of Robert Preston Taylor’s military career after his time as a Prisoner of War. Official orders, newsletters written by the chaplain, appointment books, correspondence, and activity reports are present. In addition, a significant number of sermons given while on active duty are present. The series is arranged in chronological order and in good condition.
  - Orders, 1946-1955 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Chaplain Monthly Reports, 1946-1956 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - General, 1947-1960 (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Sermons and Speeches by Others (1 of 2), 1953-1963 (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Sermons and Speeches by Others (2 of 2), 1953-1963 (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Orders, 1955-1966 (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Sermons and Speeches by Others, 1956 (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - Chaplains Quarterly Activity Reports, 1956-1957 (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - Orders of Services: Marriages, Funerals, etc., 1956-1959 (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - Chaplain Newsletters, 1957-1958 (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - Monthly Reports to Chaplains Commission; Home Mission Board, Southern Baptist Convention, 1958-1962 (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - Chaplain Newsletters, 1959-1961 (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - Sermons (1 of 2), 1959-1962 (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - Sermons (2 of 2), 1959-1962 (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - Personal Correspondence, 1961 (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - Appointment Books, 1962 (Box 4, Folder 7)
  - Chaplain Newsletter, 1962-1966 (Box 4, Folder 8)
  - Personal Correspondence, 1962-1964 (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - Sermons (1 of 2), 1963 (Box 5, Folder 2)
  - Sermons (2 of 2), 1963 (Box 5, Folder 3)
  - Appointment Books, 1963 (Box 5, Folder 4)
  - Appointment Books, 1964 (Box 5, Folder 5)
  - Sermons (1 of 2), 1964-1965 (Box 6, Folder 1)
  - Sermons (2 of 2), 1964-1965 (Box 6, Folder 2)
  - Appointment Books, 1965 (Box 6, Folder 3)
  - List of Air Force General Officers, 1966 (Box 6, Folder 4)
- Photographs, 1948-1987, undated; 4
  The Photographs series, dated 1948-1987, includes material primarily from Chaplain Taylor’s military career. Military portraits, luncheons, dinners, event attendance, and celebrations are documented. Several folders include official military photographs from a visit with Archbishop Eugenious in Crete. The series is arranged in chronological order and in good condition.
  Index Terms
  Genres
  Photographic print; Portrait photograph
  - Military Portrait, undated (Box 6, Folder 5)
  - General, undated (Box 6, Folder 6)
  - Presentation of Letter of Appreciation to Chaplain Robert P. Taylor, undated (Box 6, Folder 7)
  - Luncheon at Raleigh Hotel, Waco, TX, undated (Box 6, Folder 8)
  - Conference at Air Force Chaplain School, undated (Box 6, Folder 9)
  - Official Air Force Portraits, undated (Box 6, Folder 10)
  - Portraits, Undated (Box 6, Folder 11)
  - General, 1948, 1959, 1965-1966, undated (Box 6, Folder 12)
  - General, 1962-1966, undated (Box 6, Folder 13)
  - General, Other People, 1962-1965, undated (Box 6, Folder 14)
  - Ceremonies, Awards Given and Received, 1965-1966, undated (Box 6, Folder 15)
  - Biography, Archbishop Eugenious, Crete, Greece, Part 1 (1 of 4), 1954-1961 (Box 6, Folder 16)
  - Biography, Archbishop Eugenious, Crete, Greece, Part 1 (2 of 4), 1954-1961 (Box 6, Folder 17)
  - Biography, Archbishop Eugenious, Crete, Greece, Part 1 (3 of 4), 1954-1961 (Box 6, Folder 18)
  - Biography, Archbishop Eugenious, Crete, Greece, Part 1 (4 of 4), 1954-1961 (Box 6, Folder 19)
  - Congratulatory Celebration, 1958 (Box 6, Folder 20)
  - Conferences, 1958-1966 (Box 6, Folder 21)
  - SSMA (Soldiers’, Marines’, and Airmen’s Club) Event, 1959 (Box 6, Folder 22)
  - Luncheons and Dinners, 1959, 1962, 1965 (Box 6, Folder 23)
  - Airport Arrivals, 1960,1965 (Box 6, Folder 24)
  - Biography, Archbishop Eugenious, Crete, Greece, Part 2 (1 of 3), 1962-1963 (Box 7, Folder 1)
  - Biography, Archbishop Eugenious, Crete, Greece, Part 2 (2 of 3), 1962-1963 (Box 7, Folder 2)
  - Biography, Archbishop Eugenious, Crete, Greece, Part 2 (3 of 3), 1962-1963 (Box 7, Folder 3)
  - Presentation of Bible from Washington City Bible Study, 1963 (Box 7, Folder 4)
  - Far East Trip, 1965 April (Box 7, Folder 5)
  - Trip to Seoul, Korea, 1965 April (Box 7, Folder 6)
  - Joint Service Commendation Medal Award, 1965 June (Box 7, Folder 7)
  - Funeral of General Thomas D. White, 1965 December (Box 7, Folder 8)
  - Christian Laymen’s Luncheon at Kelly Air Force Base, 1966 (Box 7, Folder 9)
  - 191st Anniversary of the Army Chaplainry Luncheon, Pentagon, 1966 (Box 7, Folder 10)
  - Military Chaplains Association Convention, 1966 April (Box 7, Folder 11)
  - Retirement Party, 1966 July (Box 7, Folder 12)
  - Distinguished Service Medal Presentation, 1966 July (Box 7, Folder 13)
  - General, Southwest Baptist Theological Seminary, 1967-1974 (Box 7, Folder 14)
  - General, 1985 (Box 7, Folder 15)
  - United States Air Force Chaplain School Visit, 1987 June (Box 7, Folder 16)
- Publications, 1961-1991; 5
  The Publications series, dated 1961-1996, includes a history of the United States Air Force Chaplain services from its beginnings in the Army Air Unit to 1990 and several books recounting experiences of soldiers involved in the Bataan Death March, Taylor is remembered in these accounts. Also included are clippings, recruiting materials, and a history of the 31st Infantry Division. The series is arranged alphabetically, books first, and in excellent condition.
  - Books: Air Force Chaplains Volume I: The Service of Chaplains to Army Air Units 1917-1946, Air Force Chaplains Volume II: Air Force Chaplains 1940-1960, 1961, 1963 (Box 7, Folder 17)
  - Books: Air Force Chaplains Volume III: Air Force Chaplains 1961-1970, Air Force Chaplains Volume IV: Air Force Chaplains 1971-1980, 1975, 1986 (Box 7, Folder 18)
  - Books: Air Force Chaplains Volume IV: Facilitators of the Free Exercise of Religion 1981-1990, Bataan: Our Last Ditch, 1991, 1990 (Box 18, Folder 1)
  - Books: Book of Worship for United States Forces, But Not In Shame, Disciples in Uniform, Forgotten Men, 1974, 1964, 1967, 1987 (Box 18, Folder 2)
  - Books: Hero of Bataan: The Story of General Jonathan Wainwright, Love and Duty, 1987, 1992 (Box 19, Folder 1)
  - Books: The Military Chaplains Association of the United States of America, 1996 (Box 19, Folder 2)
  - Books: Prisoners of the Japanese: POWs of World War II in the Pacific, Surrender and Survival: The Experience of American POWs in the Pacific 1941 - 1945, 1994, 1985 (Box 19, Folder 3)
  - The Camel’s Calf (Shriners’ Magazine Interview), 1982 (Box 9, Folder 4)
  - Clippings, 1968, 1976 (Box 9, Folder 5)
  - Clippings, 1995, 1998 (Box 9, Folder 6)
  - Contact: Information Bulletin, United States Air Force Institute of Technology, Wright-Pattern Air Force Base, Ohio, 1954 (Box 9, Folder 7)
  - Department of the Air Force Chaplain Service Recruiting Material, 1968 (Box 9, Folder 8)
  - History of the 31st U.S. Infantry and Yearbook, 1989-1990 (Box 9, Folder 9)
  - National Chaplain Committee Meeting, Dallas, TX, Keynote Address, 1972 (Box 9, Folder 10)
  - Protestant Men of the Chapel, Program Topics, 1961 (Box 9, Folder 11)
- Audiovisual, 1962-1988, undated; 6
  The Audiovisual series is dated 1962-1988. Items include sermons and appearances Taylor made while in service of the United States Air Force as well as in civilian life. Standout items include open-reel recordings of his sermon at the Iraklion Air Station Chapel in Crete in 1963, and his final sermon as an active-duty officer given at Carswell Air Force Base on July 31, 1966. The series is arranged chronologically and in good condition.
  Cassette tape; Reel to reel tapes; Video home system (VHS) tapes
  - Open Reel: Chaplain Taylor, Meet the Guest, undated (Box 1 OVZ, Folder 1)
  - Open Reel: Brigadier General Chaplain Robert Taylor, United States Air Force Academy Baccalaureate Service, 1962 June 3 (Box 1 OVZ, Folder 2)
  - Open Reel: Sermon, Station Chapel, Iraklion Air Station, Crete, 1963 June 9 (Box 1 OVZ, Folder 3)
  - Open Reel: Worship Service at Carswell Air Force Base, 1966 July 31 (Box 1 OVZ, Folder 4)
  - Audiocassette: General Taylor’s Message, 1979 April 4 (Box 1 OVZ, Folder 5)
  - Audiocassette: Elmcrest Baptist Church, 1986 November 9 (Box 1 OVZ, Folder 6)
  - VHS: First Baptist Church, Gainesville, Texas, 1988 July 3 (Box 1 OVZ, Folder 7)